Guide to the Miriam Hapgood DeWitt Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Miriam Hapgood DeWitt Papers
1812-1990
1903-1990
YCAL MSS 277
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
11.36
25 boxes
The Miriam Hapgood DeWitt Papers consists of original and photocopied material, including letters, documents, and literary papers, related to the journalists and authors Hutchins Hapgood (1869-1944) and Neith Boyce (1872-1951), their forebears, and their circle of intellectuals, social reformers, and artists. The collection was created by their daughter Miriam Hapgood Dewitt (1906-1990), with the assistance of her sister Beatrix Hapgood Faust (1910-1994).
DeWitt, Miriam Hapgood, 1906-1990
Smith, Nathan, 1762-1829
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Edward Bright, 1991.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 25: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Associated Materials
Additional Hutchins Hapgood and Neith Boyce material can be found in the Hapgood Family Papers (YCAL MSS 41) at the Beinecke Library, and the Hapgood Family Papers (manuscript group 795) in Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Existence and Location of Copies
Some of the material in Series III, Hutchins Hapgood and Neith Boyce Correspondence Collection, was microfilmed by patron request prior to the collection being processed. Film number 2686 contains some but not all of the current contents of the 1906-1909 letters folders, as well as Neith Boyce's entire scrapbook of newspaper clippings now in Series II.
Miriam Hapgood DeWitt
Miriam Hapgood DeWitt was the daughter of the journalists and authors Hutchins Hapgood (1869-1944) and Neith Boyce (1872-1951). She was born in Florence, Italy, on November 29, 1906, and, along with her siblings Harry Boyce (1901-1918), Charles Hutchins (1904-1982) and Beatrix (1910-1994), was raised in the family's homes in New York and Provincetown, Massachusetts. As an adult, she lived in Taos, New Mexico, through 1945, then in Washington, D.C., through 1979, after which she settled in Provincetown and resided there until her death on April 16, 1990. DeWitt worked briefly for the federal government while in Washington, and also had a successful career as a painter. Her first marriage, to Edward Hamilton Bright (1894-1954) in 1930, produced two sons but ended in divorce; her second, in 1947 to the Croatian-born economist, writer, and educator Vaso Trivanovitch (ca. 1899-1949), ended at his death; and her third, in 1956 to the writer and Department of the Interior administrator John DeWitt (1910-1984), also ended in divorce.
Scope and Contents
The Miriam Hapgood DeWitt Papers consists of original and photocopied material related to the writers Hutchins Hapgood (1869-1944) and Neith Boyce (1872-1951), their forebears, and their circle of intellectuals, social reformers, and artists. The collection was created by their daughter Miriam Hapgood DeWitt (1906-1990) with the assistance of her sister Beatrix Hapgood Faust (1910-1994), as the women endeavored to gather and publish an annotated selection of their parents' correspondence while working closely with scholars interested in their parents' lives.
Although the collection contains a good selection of original items, including a diary and scrapbook, and some correspondence and literary writings, the bulk of the papers is a chronologically arranged set of copies of letters sent between Hutchins Hapgood and Neith Boyce and their friends and family. As writers covering social causes in the first two decades of the twentieth century, and founders of the amateur theatre company Provincetown Players, Hapgood and Boyce formed close lifetime associations with activists, anarchists, artists, and authors in America and abroad. DeWitt and Faust wrote and visited libraries and collections around the United States and in Europe, gathering photocopies and microfilm of letters with which they intended to build a comprehensive chronological narrative of their parents' activities, thoughts, and relationships. Their publication project never came to fruition, but the letters collection, heavily augmented by original correspondence that the Hapgood siblings had exchanged with their parents, achieves their greater goal of documenting Hapgood and Boyce's lives, largely presented in their own words.
Miriam Hapgood DeWitt's extended family is also documented in these papers, particularly her second husband, the Croatian-born husband Vaso Trivanovitch (ca. 1899-1949), and her grandfather Charles Hutchins Hapgood (1836-1917), who traveled to Labrador (1857) and extensively around the western United States (1859-1865) and the world (1865-1867). Also included are lecture notes taken by her great-uncle Hutchins Hapgood (1792-1828), who studied medicine at Dartmouth College with Dr. Nathan Smith (1762-1829).
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series: I. Miriam Hapgood DeWitt Papers (1933-1990); II. Hapgood Family Papers (1812-1988); III. Hutchins Hapgood and Neith Boyce Correspondence (1857-1954); IV. Hapgood Circle Writings (1911-1932).
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Medicine -- Study and teaching; Croatia -- Biography; Croatia -- Description and travel; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.) -- Intellectual life; Labrador (N.L.) -- Description and travel; Taos (N.M.) -- Intellectual life; West (U.S.) -- Description and travel; Autobiographies (documents); Diaries -- United States; Family papers; Lecture notes; Scrapbooks; Baker, Ray Stannard, 1870-1946; Bentley, Arthur F. (Arthur Fisher), 1870-1957; Berenson, Bernard, 1865-1959; Berenson, Mary, 1864-1945; Boyce, Henry Harrison; Boyce, Mary Ella Smith; Boyce, Neith, 1872-1951; DeBoer-Langworthy, Carol, 1942-; DeWitt, Miriam Hapgood, 1906-1990; Faust, Beatrix Hapgood, 1910-; Hapgood, Charles Hutchins, 1836-1917; Hapgood, Hutchins, 1869-1944; Hapgood, Norman, 1868-1937; Lisle, Laurie; Marcaccio, Michael D., 1946-; Rischin, Moses, 1925-; Rudnick, Lois Palken, 1944-; Trimberger, Ellen Kay, 1940-; Trivanovitch, Vaso, -1949; Boyce family; Hapgood family
- Miriam Hapgood DeWitt Papers, 1945-1990; Series I; 2.21; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Other Papers.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains correspondence and documents that have almost exclusively to do with Charles Hapgood, Miriam DeWitt, and Beatrix Faust's administration of their parents' papers at the Yale University Library, their various attempts to publish their parents' writings, and files of information they collected about people and topics relative to their parents' lives. The Correspondence subseries has three folders of letters written by the Hapgood siblings to each other, including carbon copies that were distributed to the third when just two were corresponding. The letters are filed in reverse chronological order as they were kept by DeWitt. Some additional earlier letters exchanged between the siblings are filed in Series III.
  Third-party Correspondence is both incoming and outgoing letters sent between the Hapgood siblings and various authors, librarians, and publishers. The subject matter primarily regards other researchers' publication rights and projects, or the Hapgood sisters' own photocopy requests. A set of alphabetical files for specific correspondents is followed by three folders of general correspondence. Within the alphabetical files are three folders documenting the efforts made to publish Neith Boyce's history of Richmond, New Hampshire, titled "A Town in the Forest," and her compilation of Hapgood family letters titled "The Story of an American Family." The manuscripts of both works are not here, but can be found in the Hapgood Family Papers (YCAL MSS 41).
  The general correspondence is filed in reverse chronological order as kept by DeWitt. Perhaps most notable here is a letter from DeWitt to Bernice Kent, dated November 26, 1984, in which she describes her relationship with Ernest Hemingway, and mentions that she had sold in the 1960s the letters he had written her. Transcripts of the Hemingway letters accompany the carbon copy of DeWitt's letter to Kent.
  The Other Papers subseries contains folders of notes made by the sisters while gathering, transcribing, and arranging the copies of letters written by and to their parents, and two boxes of card files related to the project. DeWitt's Subject Files hold reference material on people and places connected to the Hapgoods, primarily photocopies, clippings, etc., with just a few pieces of correspondence. A feature article on Miriam and John DeWitt from the Washington, D.C., Evening Star is also filed here.
  - Correspondence
    - Hapgood siblings letters, 1974-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
      Filed in reverse chronological order
    - Third-party correspondence
      - Bentley, Arthur F. and Imogene, 1950-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - DeBoer-Langworthy, Carol, 1975-1987 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
        Includes NEH grant application
      - Green, Carol Hurd
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: Notable American Women
      - Lisle, Laurie, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Marcaccio, Michael D., 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Marriner, Gerald L., 1974-1984 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
      - Notable American Women, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Rischin, Moses, 1965-1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Rudnick, Lois Palken, 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - "The Story of an American Family" publication project, 1945-1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - "A Town in the Forest" publication project, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
      - Trimberger, Ellen Kay
        - Correspondence, 1983-1990 (Box 2, Folder 18)
        - "Intimate Warriors" draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
        - Other writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Vorse, Mary Heaton, 1965 Jul 14 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Yale University Library, 1961-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - General correspondence, 1950-1990, undated (Box 2, Folder 23-26)
  - Other Papers
    Arranged under two headings: Letters Project and Subject Files.
    - Letters project
      - Beatrix Faust notebook, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Folder lists, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Notes from "A Victorian", undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Notes on letters, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - Notes on publications, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Notes, random, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Selection lists, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Typing lists, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - Card files, undated (Box 3–4)
    - Subject files
      - Bentley, Arthur, 1982, undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
      - Boyce, Neith, portrait photographs by Frances Benjamin Johnston (photocopies), 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 36)
      - Cook, Nilla Cram, 1982 Oct 13 (Box 5, Folder 37)
      - DeWitt, Miriam, and John, 1972 Mar 23
      - Dobbs Ferry house (John D. Flower mansion) descriptions, undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
      - Goldman, Emma, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 39)
      - Harrington, M.R., undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Hapgood chronologies, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Labor, unions, and strikes, 1977-1988
      - Luhan, Mabel Dodge, 1982, undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
      - The Masses, 1985, undated (Box 5, Folder 43)
      - National Historical Publications and Records Commission, 1983-1984 (Box 5, Folder 44)
      - Plutarch, letter on his daughter's death, undated (Box 5, Folder 45)
      - Provincetown, Massachusetts, undated
      - Provincetown Playhouse, 1960-1984 (Box 5, Folder 46)
      - Ruskin Art Club, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 47)
      - Vorse, Mary Heaton, undated (Box 5, Folder 48)
      - Writers and writing, 1950-1988
      - Miscellaneous clippings, 1974-1986 (Box 5, Folder 49)
- Hapgood Family Papers, 1812-1988; Series II; 1.46; (4 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Papers and Writings.
  The Papers subseries contains a variety of material inherited by Miriam DeWitt or copied by her from Beinecke Library's Hapgood Family Papers, Series IV (YCAL MSS 41). Photocopies are distinguished in the folder listing, but the dates shown are those of the original materials regardless if they are photocopies or originals.
  Prominent among the original items in the subseries is a scrapbook kept by Neith Boyce that holds reviews of her books clipped or transcribed from newspapers and periodicals, and a folder of contemporary ephemera related to Hutchins Hapgood that includes printed promotional material for his books and a series of lecture programs he offered, book dust jackets, and newspaper clippings about the 1938 fire that destroyed his cottage in Provincetown. There are four folders of material related to Charles H. Hapgood, brother of Miriam DeWitt. Two contain correspondence: a group of letters that document an extramarital affair between Hapgood and Mary Grand, and a psychoanalytical letter that Hapgood wrote about his parents. Also filed here is a manuscript of Hapgood's early automatic writing and other childhood documents, as well newspaper obituaries on him written by DeWitt.
  Also present are photocopies of Alfred Stieglitz's inscriptions on Hutchins Hapgood's copies of the journal Camera Work; the issues were sold at auction by the Hapgood siblings in 1982. Four files hold family genealogical material that was inherited or collected by DeWitt; the Hapgood folder has pages photocopied from The Hapgood Family (Boston, 1898), however the pages (317-318) in that volume that show the direct line to DeWitt's father are not included.
  The Writings subseries contains a collection of works written by members of the Hapgood family. In addition to literary works by Neith Boyce and Hutchins Hapgood, there are personal items such as a photocopy of a 166-page memoir by Charles Hutchins Hapgood (1836-1917), the father of Hutchins Hapgood. Apparently transcribed (with minor annotations) in 1913, it describes in some detail his sea journey to Labrador (1857) and his schooling and travel in New England (1858-1859), as well as observations made during his extensive travel around the western United States (1859-1865) and around the world (1865-1867); the final sections cover his career and later family life. The earliest item in the collection is also filed here: a small booklet in which Hutchins Hapgood (1792-1828), the great-uncle of Hutchins Hapgood (1869-1944), made careful notes of a set of medical lectures given by Dr. Nathan Smith (1762-1829). Hapgood was an 1813 graduate of Dartmouth College, where he studied with Smith, founder of the medical schools at both Dartmouth and Yale University. Five folders hold three versions of autobiographical essays covering the life of Vaso Trivanovitch (ca. 1899-1949), the second husband of Miriam DeWitt, before he emigrated from Croatia to the United States in 1919.
  Writings by Hutchins Hapgood and Neith Boyce dominate the subseries; they consist mostly of photocopies collected by DeWitt from institutions, notably Beinecke Library, with some print versions and original typescripts filed in; Boyce's story "Odd Jobs" is, for instance, in the latter category and does not appear with the bulk of her original manuscripts in the Hapgood Family Papers (YCAL MSS 41). Also original here is a financial diary kept by Hutchins Hapgood during his time at Harvard University, where he received his bachelor's degree in 1892. Beginning on September 24, 1889, it has lists of amounts paid for his books, transportation, laundry, and entertainment, including theatrics and athletics, and covers the months that he studied in Europe, from June 1893 through November 1894. The only narrative in the volume is a short preface that names the theatrical performances he had seen before arriving at college.
  - Papers
    - Ancestors, undated (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Boyce, Neith
      - Bank records, 1941-1953 (Box 6, Folder 51)
      - Letter to editor of unknown newspaper, circa 1946 (Box 6, Folder 52)
      - Poem read at funeral, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 53)
      - Scrapbook of book review clippings and transcripts, 1903-1906 (Box 6, Folder 54)
        Existence and Location of Copies
        Available through Access Services: Microfilm 2686
    - Camera Work inscriptions, undated (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Faust, Beatrix Hapgood, manuscript poetry book, circa 1920 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Genealogies
      - Boyce family, 1975-1988 (Box 6, Folder 57)
      - Collins family, undated (Box 6, Folder 58)
      - Grout family, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 59)
      - Hapgood family, 1902, undated (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - Hapgood, Charles Hutchins (1904-1982)
      - Automatic writing, circa 1918 (Box 6, Folder 61)
      - Correspondence with Mary Grand, 1957-1958, undated (Box 6, Folder 62)
      - Ephemera, 1920-1982, undated (Box 6, Folder 63)
      - Letter to Mr. Henle, circa 1954 (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - Hapgood family estate papers
      - Correspondence and documents, 1904-1975 (Box 6, Folder 65-66)
      - National Gas and Oil Corporation, 1952-1958 (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - Hapgood, Hutchins (1869-1944)
      - Ephemera, 1927-1940, undated (Box 6, Folder 68)
      - "Father's death", 1944 (Box 6, Folder 69)
        Notes taken by Miriam Hapgood DeWitt and Charles Hapgood at the time of Hutchins Hapgood's death
    - Hapgood, Norman, newspaper clipping, 1943 Jan 14 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - Indian Bureau, 1933, undated (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Miscellaneous ephemera, 1910-1988, undated (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Writings
    - Boyce, Mary E., Outlines of the History, Art, and Literature of Greece..., print version, 1894 (Box 7, Folder 73)
    - Boyce, Neith
      - Autobiography, typescript photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 74-76)
      - Diary, Italy, 1903, typescript photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 77)
        Original filed in YCAL MSS 41, box 45, folders 1388-1389
      - Folder number not used (Box 7, Folder 78)
      - Plays
        - "The Bark and The Tree," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 79)
        - "Constancy," three versions, typescript photocopies, undated (Box 7, Folder 80)
        - "The Faithful Lover," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 81)
        - "The Sea Lady," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 82)
        - "Winter's Night," print version photocopy, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 83)
      - Poems
        - "Bird of Passage," manuscript photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 84)
        - "It Rains," typescript, 1923 (Box 7, Folder 85)
        - "To H.H. at 46" and "To H.H. at 50," typescript photocopies, 1915, 1919 (Box 7, Folder 86)
      - Stories
        - "At the Baths of Lucca," print version, undated (Box 7, Folder 87)
        - "Books and Men, print version photocopy, 1915 Feb 20 (Box 7, Folder 88)
        - "The Blue Hood," galley proofs, 1914 May 2 (Box 7, Folder 89)
        - "Bring On Your Rubber-tired Hack," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 90)
        - "The Chocolate Mouse," print version photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 91)
        - "The Elder Generation," print version photocopy, 1911 April (Box 7, Folder 92)
        - "The Faithful Wife," print version photocopy, 1915 Jan 2 (Box 7, Folder 93)
        - "The Fate of an Old Town," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 94)
        - "The Forbidden City," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 95)
        - "Illusion," print version, undated (Box 7, Folder 96)
        - "Iowa to Delphi," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 97)
        - "Maddalena Speaks," print version photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 98)
        - "Mrs. Peyton Interferes," print version photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 99)
        - "My Dear Niece," print version, undated (Box 7, Folder 100)
        - "Odd Jobs for an Artist," typescript, undated (Box 7, Folder 101)
        - "Our Neighbor's Dog," manuscript photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 102)
        - "Sand," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 103)
        - "A Story of New Spain," print version, undated (Box 7, Folder 104)
        - "To the Unreasoning Nature of Man," manuscript photocopy, typescript, undated (Box 7, Folder 105)
        - "Vadsoe of Norway," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 106)
        - [Fragment of unidentified story], typescript, undated (Box 7, Folder 107)
      - War diary, manuscript and typescript photocopies, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - Hapgood, Charles Hutchins (1836-1917), memoir, typescript photocopy, circa 1913 (Box 8, Folder 109-110)
    - Hapgood, Fred, "Preface," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Hapgood, Hutchins (1792-1828), "Continuation of Smith's lectures, No. 2," manuscript, circa 1812 (Box 8, Folder 112)
    - Hapgood, Hutchins (1869-1944)
      - Articles and columns, photocopies, 1911-1914, undated (Box 8, Folder 113-114)
      - Articles and columns clipped from newspapers, 1913, undated (Box 8, Folder 115)
      - Articles and columns, miscellaneous, print versions and photocopies, 1911-1940, undated (Box 8, Folder 116)
      - Book reviews, photocopies, undated (Box 8, Folder 117)
      - Essays
        - "A Cold Enthusiast," print version, 1913 (Box 8, Folder 118)
        - "It Would Make Women Less Attractive," print version, undated (Box 8, Folder 119)
        - "The Student's Morals," typescript carbon, undated (Box 8, Folder 120)
        - Miscellaneous manuscript essays and drafts in parts, photocopies, undated (Box 8, Folder 121)
          Includes pages from "My Forty Years of Drink"
      - Financial diary, 1889-1894 (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Hapgood, Hutchins, and Neith Boyce
      - "Dialogue," typescript, circa 1917 (Box 8, Folder 123)
        Circa 1980 typescript annotated by DeWitt: "Written not later than 1918"; original holograph filed in YCAL MSS 41, box 45, folder 1392
      - "Enemies," print version photocopy, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - Hapgood, Powers
      - "Men and Coal," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 8, Folder 125)
      - "Journal," typescript photocopy, 1924-1925 (Box 8, Folder 126)
    - Trivanovitch, Vaso
      - Autobiography, typescript and manuscript, undated (Box 8, Folder 127-128)
      - Autobiography, typescript, undated (Box 9, Folder 129)
      - Autobiography, typescript carbon, undated (Box 9, Folder 130)
      - Miscellaneous autobiographical writings, typescript and manuscript, undated (Box 9, Folder 131)
      - Correspondence, 1946, undated (Box 9, Folder 132)
- Hutchins Hapgood and Neith Boyce Correspondence, 1857-1954; Series III; 5.52; (13.5 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: "The Undiscover'd Country," and Letters Collection.
  The series contains letters written to and by Hutchins Hapgood and Neith Boyce, as collected in photocopies, transcripts, and original manuscripts. The first subseries holds two copies of an undated book proposal made by John DeWitt, the third husband of Miriam Hapgood DeWitt. With a working title of "The Undiscover'd Country," the volume was to be composed of letters written between Hutchins Hapgood and Neith Boyce before the death of their son Harry [called "Boyce"] in the 1918 flu pandemic, and others written afterward between Hapgood and Boyce and their friends, all demonstrating the profound impact that tragedy had on their lives. The proposal is filed in this series rather than in Series II with other family writings because it is primarily correspondence, and may hold transcripts that do not appear in the Letters Collection subseries that follows.